Rafat Ahmed

Senior Software Engineer

Location: Rajarbag, Dhaka **Mobile:** 01911750945

Mail: rafatahmedorik@gmail.com

Github: Rafat Ahmed LinkedIn :Rafat Ahmed

OVERVIEW

Senior software engineer and backend architect with over 9 years of industry experience across different industries, platforms, systems, and services. Over the last 7 years, I've been completely focused on web development. I love designing infrastructures and I've experience working as a Web backend Architect. I also have efficient knowledge of the frontend. Always try to maintain all the industry standards from development to deployment, such as test-driven development, proper use of git-flow, and all containerization technologies.

SKILLS

Javascript Database php Nodejs | nestJs | AdonisJs | react | Laravel | symfony | composer | MySQL | postgres | mariadb express | typescript | jest PHPUnit | Xdebug **Software Engineering** Cloud **Searching Tools** Git | jira | scrum | docker | design Aws lambda | aws code pipeline | Algolia | mysql full-text search | EC2 | S3 bucket | aws cloud front patterns | sdlc | kitemaker elastic search

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer at Green Pants Studio

May 2024 - present

https://www.greenpantsstudio.com/

Role: project coordinator, development

Technologies: Nodejs, NestJS, postgres, AWS, react, NextJs, typescript, lambda

- Developed and maintained scalable web applications for auction services using Node.js (NestJS), React, Next.js, TypeScript, PostgreSQL, and AWS Lambda, supporting multi-vendor systems.
- Designed a flexible multi-vendor seller system, providing full auction control, customer management, and product listings for sellers
- Integrated SendGrid for real-time email notifications, enhancing buyer-seller interactions and engagement.
- Conducted **unit testing**, achieving 53% code coverage with **Jest**, and utilized **CloudWatch** for proactive monitoring and rapid issue resolution.
- Implemented real-time auction with live video streaming for immersive user experiences.
- Contributed to the continuous improvement of the auction platform, ensuring reliability and seamless scaling as user demand grows.
- Spearheaded system performance optimization and real-time data processing to support thousands of concurrent users.
- Collaborated closely with cross-functional teams, aligning technical solutions with business goals to enhance platform capabilities.

Senior Software Engineer at Cefalo Bangladesh Ltd.

December 2021 - April 2024

https://www.cefalo.com/en/

Role: project coordinator, development

Technologies: nodejs, express, postgres, Kitemaker, AWS, python, react, nextjs, typescript, mysql, lambda

- Developed microservice-based web applications for rental service using node is and for client using nextis. https://leid.no/
- Instead of buying, people can borrow tools. After placing an order the user will get a QR code. They are using that he/she can take the ordered tools for a time.
- Developing subscription system using PHP, Laravel, node, and Express that is already in use in several sites https://www.friflyt.no/
- . In the subscription system, we can provide monthly and yearly subscriptions based on the requirements.
- using node js we serve the data for the from elastic search also in aws lambda we used node js for storing data to elastic search
- creating custom node modules for the server-side API handling, and unit testing code coverage (82.4%) using JEST.

Senior Software Engineer at Thrive EdTech

May 2020 - October 2021

https://www.thrive.com.bd/

Role: System architecture design, development

Technologies: react, laravel, mysql, digital ocean, google cloud, jira, git, redis, python, dgraph, django

- Developed microservice-based web applications for learning analytics.
- Teachers and students get their results based on exams. Also, they can see their progress with the time.
- Developed school management so students and teacher can easily share their current progress, Also routine management was one of the big features. integrated third-party communication services like Zoom, and Google Meet for virtual classrooms.

Senior Software Engineer at Rapid Web Services

October 2016 - April 2020

https://www.rapidws.net/

Role: Software engineer and team lead

Technologies: laravel, mysql, react, aws, jira, git

- Developed REST API based inventory application for various business tracking, and real-time data visualization using Kibana.
- Implemented user-defined business models for different organizations. Also, implement data encryption for security.
- Used Elasticsearch to manage data retrieval. It improved the efficiency of data retrieval by more than 1.3%.
- Implemented docker for fast development and deployment.

EDUCATION

BSc. Engineering in Computer Science & Engineering

from Ahsanullah University of Science & Technology

REFERENCES

Md. Abul Kasem Shimanto

Software Development Engineer @ LivePerson siamnto604@gmail.com

Shariar Shaikot

Frontend Developer @Frontmen mail2shariar@gmail.com